<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Scotland's right to Caledonia (formerly called Darien), and the legality of its settlement asserted in three several memorials presented to His Majesty in May 1699 / by the Lord President of the Session, and Lord Advocate on behalf of the Company of Scotland, Trading to Africa and the Indies.</title>
            <author>Company of Scotland Trading to Africa and the Indies.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34148</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5599B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3522</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11882881</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11882881</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50338</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34148)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50338)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 23:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Scotland's right to Caledonia (formerly called Darien), and the legality of its settlement asserted in three several memorials presented to His Majesty in May 1699 / by the Lord President of the Session, and Lord Advocate on behalf of the Company of Scotland, Trading to Africa and the Indies.</title>
                  <author>Company of Scotland Trading to Africa and the Indies.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 34.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Columbia University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Darien Scots' Colony, 1698-1700.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Commercial policy.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  1689-1745.</term>
               <term>Panama --  Colonization.</term>
               <term>Panama --  Discovery and exploration.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50338:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50338:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SCOTLAND'S <hi>RIGHT</hi> to <hi>CALEDONIA</hi> (Formerly called <hi>DARIEN</hi>) And the Legality of its Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement, aſſerted in Three ſeveral Memorials preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to His Majeſty in <hi>May</hi> 1699.</p>
            <p>BY The Lord Preſident of the Seſſion and Lord Advocate, on behalf of the Company of <hi>Scotland,</hi> Trading to <hi>Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> and the <hi>Indies.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Quod enim eſt nullius, per occupationem acquiritur ejus Dominium. Puffend. de Jur.
<bibl>
                  <hi>Nat. &amp; Gent.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:50338:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50338:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Three following Memorials were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to His Majeſty in</hi> May 1699. <hi>by the Lord Preſident of the Seſſion, and Lord Advocat, on behalf of the Company of</hi> Scotland, <hi>Trading to</hi> Africa <hi>and the</hi> Indies, <hi>aſſerting the Legality of their Settlement in</hi> Darien.</head>
            <div n="1" type="memorial">
               <head>1ſt. <hi>MEMORIAL.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Eſtabliſhment of the Company of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Trading to <hi>Africa</hi> and the <hi>Indies,</hi> was firſt prepared by an Act of Parliament 1693. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viting and Encouraging Perſons in General, to enter into Societies, and Companies, for carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on a Trade to whatſoever Kingdoms, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie or parts of the World, not being in War with His Majeſty, and thereafter perfected by the Act of Parliament 1695, and a Charter thereon under the Great Seal, whereby the ſaid Company was fully Settled with all the Powers, Priviledges, and Immunities in uſe to be granted in ſuch caſes, and particularly with Power to plant Colonies, and build Cities, Towns, and Forts in <hi>Aſia, Africa,</hi> or <hi>America,</hi> upon Places not Inhabited, or upon any other Place, by Conſent of the Natives, and Inhabitants thereof, and not poſſeſs'd by any <hi>European</hi> Prince or State.</p>
               <p>The Settling of this Company was ſo accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the whole Kingdom, abounding always with Men, and of late Years, very deſirous to enlarge Trade and Commerce, That the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany's
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50338:3"/>Books being once opened, Subſcriptions for a vaſt Sum were compleated long before the Day prefix'd by the Act of Parliament, and there were few Perſons or Families of any Account within the Kingdom, who were not therein par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly concerned.</p>
               <p>But tho' the Subſcriptions were ſoon compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Advances made, as readily as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd; yet the Directors and Managers, did proceed with great Deliberation, not being more Cautious to Conceal the Place where they were deſign'd for, than Careful to make ſuch a Choice, as might be exactly in the Terms of their Act and Patent, To wit, <hi>Either not Inhabited, or freely Conſented to, by the Natives, and not poſſeſs'd by any</hi> European <hi>Prince or State, and ſo lyable to no Exception.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In purſuance of theſe Reſolutions, The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany prepared Men, and Proviſions, and ſet out their Ships, and in the Month of <hi>November</hi> 1698, arrived on the Noth-ſide of the <hi>Isthmus</hi> of <hi>Darien</hi> in <hi>America,</hi> they pitched upon a Place never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore poſſeſs'd by the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> and after formal and diſtinct Treaties, obtained the Conſent and Good-will of all the Neighbouring Natives and People.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>French</hi> raiſe a Clamour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Settlement, as an Invaſion of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Poſſeſſions and Dominions, in as much as the Place where the Company hath fixed, lyes as it were in the Middle and Boſom of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Countries, having <hi>Carthagenae</hi> on the Eaſt, and <hi>Porto-Bello</hi> on the Weſt, and <hi>Panama</hi> on the South, which is alſo alledged to be contrary to the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50338:3"/>Treaties betwixt the King of <hi>Great Brittain</hi> and the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> whereby all theſe Countrie's are yeilded and conformed to the <hi>Spaniards</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If theſe parts of <hi>America</hi> had been wholly Void and Uninhabited, when the <hi>Spaniards</hi> made their firſt Diſcoveries, and Plantations there, the Queſtion had certainly proceeded upon the head of Occupation, the only Ground acknowledg'd by all Lawyers to determine the Property of all Waſte and Uninhabited Countries, where a formal Diviſion hath not Interveened, as <hi>Grotius</hi> in particular, in his Second Book <hi>de jure Belli</hi> doth abundantly clear, and then the <hi>Spaniards</hi> muſt have further Subſumed, That as they found theſe Countries Waſte, ſo they were the Occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piers and Poſſeſſors thereof; and in Special, that they were the firſt Occupiers and Poſſeſſors of the <hi>Iſthmus</hi> of <hi>Darien,</hi> and the Place where the Company hath Settled, it being moſt certain, that Occupation gives no Right, ſave in ſo far as the Real and Actual Poſſeſſion extends.</p>
               <p>But ſeing on the other hand, it is Nottour, and by all Acknowledg'd, That the <hi>Spaniards</hi> did not find theſe Parts Waſte, and Uninhabited, this Argument muſt neceſſarly fall; and all that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> can now Plead, is either preſent Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which the Company's Patent owns to be a ſufficient Right to any <hi>European</hi> Prince or State, or the above-mention'd Treaties, as excluſive of the King of <hi>Great Brittain's</hi> Subjects.</p>
               <p>For clearing then the Claim and Point of Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, The Company denies that ever the <hi>Spaniard</hi> had any Poſſeſſion of the Place where they have Planted; and its obviouſly Incumbent
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50338:4"/>to the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> if they alledge Poſſeſſion, to prove and inſtruct their Alledgance for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany's Argument being Negative, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Spaniards</hi> did never Poſſeſs the Country where the Company hath Settled, it Undeniably proves it ſelf, as all Lawiers affirm, unleſs the contrary, to wit, The <hi>Spaniards</hi> Poſſeſſion, be evidently made out and proved, which is impoſſible; Nor do the <hi>Spaniards</hi> pretend to prove the ſame; But their Alledgance is, That in theſe large Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries of <hi>America,</hi> it were plainly Capricious to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the Actual Poſſeſſion of every particular Place; But ſince they have the Uncontraverted Right and Poſſeſſion of <hi>Carthagena, Porto-Bello,</hi> and <hi>Panama,</hi> which are the Extremities that in a manner environ the <hi>Isthmus</hi> of <hi>Darien,</hi> their Poſſeſſion of theſe Places, muſt infer a Poſſeſſion of the Interjacent Country in which the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany hath Settled, and conſequently, that the Company hath Encroached upon, and Invaded their Right: And further, its ſaid, That the <hi>Spaniards</hi> have actually poſſeſs'd Gold and Silver Mines in <hi>Darien,</hi> much nearer to the Company's Settlement than <hi>Carthgena,</hi> or theſe other Places, and have conſtantly been in uſe to Seize and make Prize of all Ships coming upon the Coaſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Porto-Bello</hi> and <hi>Carthagena,</hi> as Invaders of their Poſſeſſions, tho' theſe Ships did really pertain to Friends and Allies:</p>
               <p>To all which, It is anſwered, 1mo. That the above-mentioned Places belonging to the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> are very far diſtant from the Settlement of the Company, <hi>Carthagena</hi> above Fifty, and <hi>Porto-bello</hi> and <hi>Panama</hi> above Thirty Leagues, which Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances are more then ſufficient to render Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50338:4"/>diſtinct, both as to Right and Poſſeſſion. 2do. It's certain, that <hi>Carthagena, Porto-bello</hi> or <hi>Panama,</hi> cannot be underſtood to have unlimited Territories; if then their Territories be limited, it belongs to the makers of the Objection to ſhow, that the Limits of theſe places do reach to, and comprehend the Place poſſeſs'd by the Company, which neither the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> nor any for them, will ever be able to prove, by the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or any known Rule, or Cuſtom in ſuch Caſes.</p>
               <p>It hath already been Notic'd, That tho' theſe Countries had been wholly Void, when the <hi>Spaniards</hi> begun to Plant there, they could only by their Poſſeſſion have appropriat as far as they did poſſeſs, and that what was not poſſeſs'd, would have remain'd free, to be appropriated by the Occupation, and poſſeſſion of any other People, a Rule Uncontraverted amongſt all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on the Face of the Earth.</p>
               <p>But the Caſe of <hi>America</hi> being, That before any Plantations were Settled there, by the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards,</hi> the Natives were undoubtedly the Poſſeſſors and Proprietors. It follows neceſſarly, That Colonies coming to Settle among them, muſt derive Right from them, and that either by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, Surrender, or Conqueſt, it being impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible in the caſe of Countries inhabited, there can be any other Manner or Mean of Acquiſition; But ſo it is, That the <hi>Spaniards</hi> acquiring after this manner, neither could, nor can pretend to have Right to more than did pertain to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple where they Settled, whether by Conſent, Surrender or Conqueſt.</p>
               <p>Whence it neceſſarly follows, That ſince <hi>Darien</hi> was a diſtinct Country, and the Inhabitants
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50338:5"/>thereof a diſtinct People, from thoſe Countries and Nations, where the <hi>Spaniards</hi> have hitherto Settled whether by Conſent, Surrender, or Conqueſt; The <hi>Spaniards</hi> cannot pretend to extend their Right beyond that of their Predeceſſors, and the People &amp; Country of <hi>Darien</hi> muſt ſtill be as free from the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> as they were from their Predeceſſors; and conſequently, that the Company coming to poſſeſs with the <hi>Dariens</hi> Conſent, and by their Right, muſt be in the like Condition, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways lyable to either the Claim, or Complaint of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> That the Country and Natives of <hi>Darien</hi> did never ſubmit to, or were conquered by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> muſt ſtand as a ſure Poſition, unleſs the contrary be proven: But further, it is alſo certain, That the <hi>Dariens</hi> were never Repute to have any Dependency even on the great Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires of <hi>Mexico</hi> and <hi>Peru,</hi> much leſs upon the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle places of <hi>Carthagena, Porto-bello,</hi> or <hi>Panama:</hi> Beſides, The <hi>Dariens</hi> have been in frequent War with the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> ſince their firſt arrival into theſe Parts, and were never to this day Conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: All which being atteſted by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and other Travellers, who have Written on this Subject; It appears to be beyond Controverſy, That the Company having Settled with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of theſe <hi>Dariens,</hi> muſt have the ſame Right, with the ſame Priviledges and Freedom of Trade which the <hi>Dariens</hi> had, and that both are equally free from all the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Pretenſions.</p>
               <p>It is a known Caſe that an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man one <hi>Sharp,</hi> having join'd with the <hi>Dariens</hi> againſt the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> invaded their Territories; he was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed by the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> as guilty of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50338:5"/>Robbery and Piracy, but was acquitted, becauſe he acted by Commiſſion from one of the <hi>Darien</hi> Princes, which is an undeniable Evidence, that this Prince and his Countrey were judged to be independent on the <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> may alſo have wrought Mines of Gold and Silver within the Iſthmus; but no ſuch poſſeſſion can ſupport their Complaint: The neareſt poſſeſſion of Mines that they can pretend was in Captain <hi>Diego</hi>'s Country, on the Gulf of <hi>Darien,</hi> more than 15 Leagues diſtant from the Company's Settlement: Neither did the <hi>Spaniard</hi> get theſe Mines by Conqueſt, or Purchaſe, but by a plain ſtipulate Permiſſion from Captain <hi>Diego,</hi> and his people, which changed not the Property; And upon Breach of Conditions, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were quickly caſt out, ſo that when the Company came to ſettle on the Iſthmus, it was fully cleared of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> &amp; all their pretences.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Carthagena, Portobello</hi> and <hi>Panama,</hi> are adjacent to, and do in a manner environ the Iſthmus of <hi>Darien;</hi> But that this Vicinity gives to the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> no Claim of Right, is evident from many Inſtances; <hi>Tangier, Cheuta</hi> and <hi>Mamora,</hi> ly in the Boſom of the Empire of <hi>Morocco,</hi> and yet belong to <hi>European</hi> Princes; The <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> have Neighbouring Settlements upon the River <hi>Gambo</hi> in <hi>Africk,</hi> and all along the Coaſt of <hi>Africk</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and other <hi>European</hi> Princes have their Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlements intermixed and contiguous, where they Trade with all Freedom, without any mutual Impeachment. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> have both Plantations upon the Iſland of <hi>Newfoundland,</hi> and the <hi>Dutch</hi> in time of Peace ſettled upon <hi>Long-Iſland,</hi> and the adjacent Countrey environed on all hands
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50338:6"/>by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Plantations, and yet no War en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, but the <hi>Dutch</hi> continued their poſſeſſion till the Exchange was made for <hi>Suranam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleets do neceſſarly paſs betwixt the Cape of <hi>Florida</hi> belonging to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and the <hi>Bahama</hi> Iſlands, yet the <hi>Engliſh</hi> poſſeſs themſelves of the ſaid Iſlands, and have alſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times ſettled at <hi>Port-Royal</hi> in the bottom of the Bay of <hi>Campiechy</hi> in the Gulf of <hi>Mexico,</hi> for cutting of Logwood, and have thence removed and ſettled again at their pleaſure. The <hi>French</hi> have alſo endeavoured to ſettle in the Bay of <hi>Mex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ico,</hi> and lately and more cloſely in the <hi>Samblas</hi> Iſlands on the Coaſt of <hi>Darien;</hi> They likewiſe ſettled a Colony in <hi>Petitguavis</hi> in <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> and in <hi>Guiana</hi> on the Continent, notwithſtanding of the Vicinity of the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> The <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Portugueſe</hi> have their Reſpective Plantations on the Coaſt of <hi>Braſil,</hi> to which the <hi>Spaniards</hi> pretend Right as well as to the Iſthmus of <hi>Darien,</hi> ſuch as the Iſlands of <hi>Cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſao,</hi> and <hi>Bowane,</hi> near to <hi>Carthagena</hi> on the Eaſt, and <hi>Suranam</hi> and others upon the Continent, and yet never quarrelled. It is granted that the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> in their exceſſive Jealouſie, and upon the Pretext that by Treaties, none were to Trade in their Ports or Harbours, ſuch as <hi>Carthagena,</hi> and <hi>Porto-bello</hi> without their Licence, have ſeized and made prize of the Ships that they have found upon the Coaſt betwixt the ſaid Places; But firſt, they did this upon pretext of the ſaid Treaties. Secondly, Injury and Violence make no Right.</p>
               <p>And thirdly, it is moſt certain when the <hi>Spaniards</hi> have been overcomeand beat off in ſuch Attempts, and forced to ſuffer both <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> to cut Logwood on that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50338:6"/>Coaſt, yet the <hi>Spaniards</hi> did never complain of any Violation of Right, as knowing perfectly they had none, as may be ſeen in <hi>Dampier, Wafer,</hi> and other writers.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> at firſt endeavoured to amuſe the World, with the Popes Gift of the <hi>West-Indies,</hi> and after the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s becoming King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and in the Right of that Crown, claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Benefit of the Popes Gift of the <hi>Eaſt-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> he aſſumed the Magnifick Title of <hi>Indiarum Rex:</hi> Yet he was never able to make good his Right, or exclude others by theſe empty Names; but in all Competitions the Pretentions of <hi>Spain,</hi> did either reſolve in Occupation of what was void or ſurrendered, or conqueſt of what was poſſeſs'd by Natives; and that Title was never much regarded, either by <hi>Spain, Portugal,</hi> or any other Prince Popiſh or Proteſtant.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Head which may be pleaded for the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> is, the Treaties that have been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Crowns of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spain.</hi> But <hi>1mo.</hi> Granting that the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> will never diſown any Treaty betwixt their King (whom GOD long preſerve and proſper) may be concerned, where are theſe Treaties that exclude either the <hi>Scots</hi> or <hi>Engliſh,</hi> from poſſeſſing <hi>Darien?</hi> if not inhabited, or where Inhabited, with conſent of the Inhabitants? If the <hi>Spaniard</hi> propone upon theſe Treaties, they muſt produce them. 2do. All to be found in the latter Treaties betwixt the ſaid Crowns, ſuch as the Treatie 1667, and the Treatie 1670, which may be underſtood to be the only Regulating Treaties in this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is that in the former, The King of <hi>Spain</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliges himſelf not to moleſt the King of <hi>England,</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:50338:7"/>or his Subjects in their Plantations in <hi>America,</hi> theſe particulars enumerated not by way of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, but becauſe ſome of them had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traverted. And that in the other Treaty 1670, It is agreed in the 7th. Article, That the King of <hi>Great Brittain,</hi> and <hi>His Heirs and Succeſſors,</hi> ſhall have, hold, and poſſeſs, with full Right of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, Property, and Poſſeſſion, all Lands, Regions, Iſles, Colonies, and Lordſhips, ſituated in the <hi>West-Indies,</hi> or any part of <hi>America,</hi> which his ſaid Majeſty, or his Subjects, did then hold or poſſeſs, So that no contraverſie on any pretence, was thereafter to be moved on that Subject. And in the eight Article, That the Subjects of the ſaid King ſhould abſtain from all Commerce, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation, in the Ports and Places, having Forts, Caſtles, or Staples for Merchandiſe, poſſeſſed by either of them. To wit, That the Subjects of <hi>Great Brittain</hi> ſhould not Trade, nor Sail to the Ports nor Places, which the King of <hi>Spain</hi> hath in the <hi>VVeſt-Indies,</hi> nor the Subjects of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> Trade nor Sail to the Places, which the King of <hi>Great Brittain</hi> there poſſeſſes, without Licence given <hi>hincinde,</hi> in the Terms therein ſet down. By which it plainly appears, that all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed to, was, and is, That the Kings and their Subjects reſpectively, ſhould forbear Injuries, as likewiſe to Trade and Navigate without Licence in the Ports, Caſtles, and Staples, to either of them belonging, which can no ways exclude the King of <hi>Great Brittain</hi> and his Subjects from Trading, or making new Plantations in to ſuch Places in <hi>America,</hi> as either are not inhabited, or where the King of <hi>Spain</hi> hath no Right. The <hi>Spaniard</hi> may poſitively pretend, that the Treaties provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50338:7"/>to the King of <hi>England,</hi> and his Subjects of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain particular Places, and generally what they then poſſeſs'd in the <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> may be conſtrued an Exception, and import (as it were) an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement, that the reſt of the <hi>Weſt Indies</hi> did belong to the Crown of <hi>Spain.</hi> But, 1mo, The Places provided to the King of <hi>England</hi> and his Subjects are only enumerate for the greater Cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Security, becauſe ſome of them had been taken from the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and thereupon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traverted. And, 2do, It is evident by the foreſaid eight Articles, the Reſerve of Trade is equally and mutually provided, and reſtricted to the King of <hi>Great Brittain</hi> and the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> their reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pective Poſſeſſions; ſo that nothing can be eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite from theſe Treaties, to give the King of <hi>Spain</hi> the Right to the whole <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> excepting the foreſaid places poſſeſſed by the King of <hi>England,</hi> nor to ty up the King of <hi>Brittain</hi> and his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, from <hi>making new</hi> lawful Acquiſitions in theſe Parts. <hi>But it is agreed to,</hi> That they ſhould ſecure the one, the other in their reſpective Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions; And thus theſe Treaties have been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways underſtood, nor have they hindred the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to enlarge their Poſſeſſions in the <hi>Weſt Indies</hi> upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Occaſions, which certainly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs as much if not more to the <hi>Scots.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="memorial">
               <head>2d. MEMORIAL, By the ſame.</head>
               <p>THe Company of <hi>Scotland</hi> Trading to <hi>Africa</hi> and the <hi>Indies,</hi> having by the other Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial, endeavoured to clear the Juſtice of their Proceedings, as to their Settling a Plantation in the <hi>Iſthmus</hi> of <hi>Darien</hi> in <hi>America,</hi> do further in all Humility Repreſent,</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:50338:8"/>
               <p n="1">1mo, That there was never any Enterprize of a more National Concern, than the foreſaid Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is to the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> the Erecting and Eſtabliſhing of the ſaid Company, was the Unanimous Deſire and Satisfaction of the Nation, all Perſons almoſt, and Families of any Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, did readily ſubſcribe for, and advance conſiderable Sums, for carrying on the Deſigns of the Company, much above what could have been expected. The Succeſs the Company hath had, in overcoming Difficulties, and fixing upon a Place that appears ſo advantageous to Trade and Commerce, hath likewiſe raiſed the Expectation and Deſire of its Continuance and Proſperity, to a far higher Degree than ever was known in any Buſineſs of this Nature: And, <hi>Laſtly,</hi> it is moſt certain, That nothing could be more Grievous and Afflicting to the whole Nation, without Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, than that this Undertaking, ſo far and ſo happily advanced, ſhould meet with the leaſt Diſcouragement, eſpecially from ſuch, whoſe Countenance and Aſſiſtance is ſo earneſtly cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               <p n="2">2do, It appears from the whole Circumſtances of this Affair, That the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation can have no Prejudice, but rather Advantage by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Undertaking: For, <hi>Firſt,</hi> If it ſhall be profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, the Profit evidently redounds to their Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Subjects and good Neighbours. <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>Engliſh</hi> have free Acceſs, to come in and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the Profit, when they pleaſe. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Product of the Place is probably like to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt neither of Tobacco nor Suggars, the great Commodities of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Plantations, but of ſuch Goods and Commodities, as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> do not afford. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It is true, That by the Act
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50338:8"/>of Parliament, and Patent of the Company, all Ships imployed by the Company, are to return to the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> with their Effects: But it is as true, That the ſaid Act and Patent did bear the Liberty and Priviledge of a Free Port, and Mercat for all Strangers that ſhall be pleaſed to Trade with them, who are not under the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Obligation, but may come and go with their Return whether they pleaſe, which cannot but be of Advantage to the whole <hi>Engliſh</hi> Plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as to a Free Courſe of Trade. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> It is likeways granted, That by the foreſaid Act of Parliament, the Ships, Goods and Effects what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever belonging to the ſaid Company, are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared free of all Cuſtoms and other Duties, for the ſpace of 21 Years, but then four of the ſaid Years are already run, and this ſmall Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was needful to begin ſo great a Work, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of probably the Profit can little more than equal the Expenſes for all that ſpace; And beſides, the Duties of Tobacco and Sugar, not of the Growth of the ſaid Plantation, are excepted, and not diſcharged: And alſo it is evident, That if the Plantation proſper, the foreſaid ſhort Diſcharge of Cuſtoms, and other Duties, will be richly compenſed by the great Increaſe of Trade, and conſequently of His Majeſties Cuſtoms, that may for thereafter be thence expected. And, <hi>Sixth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> The Company and Plantation cannot reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably threaten any Diminution of His Majeſties Cuſtoms in <hi>England;</hi> but on the contrary, this Plantation promiſing a new Trade, far different from the Trade of all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Plantations, and offering to all, the Liberty of a Free Port, muſt rather increaſe the Trade of <hi>England,</hi> both to the King and Subjects Advantage.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:50338:9"/>
               <p>As for the Objection, That the Company, by the Immunity they have from Cuſtoms and Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, may Import, and then as freely Export, and ſo underſell any other Nation, during that Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity: Its Anſwered, That the Company in <hi>England</hi> have almoſt the ſame Priviledge, ſince, if they pleaſe to Export after their Return from the Plantations, they are allowed to do it freely with a full Draw-back, excepting only 3 or 4 <hi>per Cent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3tio, It is with Submiſſion Repreſented, That in all Appearance, if the Company of <hi>Scotland</hi> had not ſeized the foreſaid Poſt in <hi>Darien,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> had certainly taken it: And now, that it is diſcovered to be ſo advantageous for Trade, it is not to be doubted, but that the <hi>French,</hi> who ſhew ſuch Earneſtneſs to have the <hi>Scots</hi> excluded, will certainly, if any ſuch thing ſhould happen, poſſeſs themſelves of it, not only to the Hurt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Plantations, but to the far greater Prejudice, if not the Ruin of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in the <hi>Indies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore, All things truly and juſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, it is hoped, that not only the <hi>Engliſh</hi> will become more and more favourable to ſo good a Deſign, but that even the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> will the more eaſily acquieſce to Reaſon and Juſtice, that they ſee a more Powerful Competitor ready to catch hold of an Advantage, that cannot be ſo ſafe for them in the Hands of any other Nation, as in the Poſſeſſion of the foreſaid Company.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="memorial">
               <head>3d. <hi>MEMORIAL, By the ſame.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Company of <hi>Scotland</hi> Trading to <hi>Africa</hi> and the <hi>Indies,</hi> being endued with very ample Priviledges, hath ſettled a Colony <hi>at Dari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en,</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:50338:9"/>a Countrey very fit and proper for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, not only for the Richneſs of the Soil and Mines, but likeways by its Situation for Trade.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> have the moſt conſiderable Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and Plantations in <hi>America,</hi> and are not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, that any other Nation, or People ſhould have ſhare of the Advantages and Benefits they draw from thence, which is not Singular in the preſent Caſe, becauſe they have ever withſtood all Planters, either upon the Continent, or <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rican</hi> Iſlands, by Acts of Violence and Hoſtility, as if every Settlement in <hi>America</hi> were an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachment upon the Right of <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is lately a Memorial offered in behalf of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> to one of the Secretaries of State of the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> to the Effect following.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" rend="margQuotes" type="memorandum">
                  <body>
                     <p>My Lord Ambaſſador of <hi>Spain</hi> finding himſelf oblig'd, by expreſs Order, to repreſent to His Majeſty of <hi>Brittain</hi> what follows, Prays Mr. <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> to repreſent to his ſaid Majeſty, That the King his Maſter, being informed from ſeveral parts, and laſt of all, by the Governour of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vana,</hi> of the Inſult and Attempt of ſome <hi>Scots</hi> Ships, equipt with Men and Ammunition neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, who endeavours to poſt themſelves in the Soverign Dominions of His Majeſty in <hi>America,</hi> and particularly in the Province of <hi>Darien.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His Majeſty received this Information with Diſſatisfaction, as a Mark of little Amity, and a Rupture of the Alliance which is betwixt the two Crowns, which His Majeſty hath always obſerved very Religiouſly, and from which ſo much Advantage and Profit hath reſulted, both to His Majeſty and his Subjects, after which good Correſpondence, His Majeſty did not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50338:10"/>ſuch ſudden Attempts &amp; Inſults from His Majeſtys Subjects, and that in time of Peace, without any Pretext or Cauſe, in the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward part of his Dominions.</p>
                     <p>All that the King deſires, That this be preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to His Majeſty of <hi>Brittain,</hi> and that His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty is very ſenſible of ſuch Hoſtilities and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Procedures, againſt which, His Majeſty will take ſuch Meaſures as are convenient.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>London, <date>May 3d. 1699.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>THe Charge is great, and if it can be made appear, that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> is Invaded, as is pretended, it is but Reaſon there ſhould be juſt Reparation.</p>
               <p>It muſt be acknowledged, That it is a fair way of dealing, that the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Rights and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions are thus aſſerted by Memorial, and an Opportunity afforded, and that the whole World may be ſatisfied, that His Sacred Majeſty, the King of <hi>Great Brittain,</hi> hath granted no Patent to His Subjects in <hi>Scotland</hi> diſagreeable to Treaties with <hi>Spain,</hi> and that the <hi>Scots</hi> Company have not exceeded the Limits of their Patent, to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There may be many Reaſons offered to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy <hi>Spain,</hi> and all other Nations of <hi>Europe,</hi> except the <hi>French,</hi> that if the <hi>Scots</hi> had not ſettled in that <hi>Isthmus,</hi> or if they were now to remove from it, the ſame would be poſſeſs'd by another People, more dangerous to the Intereſt of <hi>Spain,</hi> and in due time it may be made appear, that the <hi>Scots</hi> Settlement is for the Honour of the King, &amp; the Intereſt of <hi>England,</hi> but the preſent deſign is only to ſatisfie the World, that the Patent granted by His Majeſty, was agreeable to the Treaty with
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50338:10"/>
                  <hi>Spain,</hi> and that the <hi>Scots</hi> Company have not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the Terms of their Patent, and that they have Right to what they poſſeſs in the <hi>Iſthmus</hi> of <hi>Darien,</hi> according to the Law of Nations, and that moſt part of the Nations in <hi>Europe</hi> have ſettled Plantations in the <hi>American</hi> Iſlands, or Continent, upon no other Foundation than the <hi>Scots.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is the Intereſt and Policy of all Governments, to improve the Natural Product of a Countrey, and to encourage Forreign Trade.</p>
               <p>The Experience of all Nations makes appear, That nothing contributes ſo effectually to theſe ends, as Forreign Plantations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scotland</hi> is amongſt the laſt of the Nations of <hi>Europe,</hi> in ſettling Forreign Plantations, tho' there be few that can propoſe more Advantage that way, becauſe the Nation affords many Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of Manufacture, and abounds in Men, which is the greateſt Riches, as well as the Strength of a Nation; Yet for want of Forreign Plantations, many have been uſeleſs and burdenſome to their Native Countrey, and have been conſtrained to ſerve Abroad in Forreign Wars, or into Plantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of other Countreys: And it is to be obſerved, that wherever they have planted, they have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed and multiplied, as particularly in <hi>Ireland;</hi> but no part of the Benefit does accrue to their Native Countrey.</p>
               <p>The Nation has very long deſired Forreign Settlements of their own, and did make ſome At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts that way, which proved ineffectual for want of due Encouragement, but His Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, as Father of his Countrey, regarding the Welfare of it, did endue the ſame with ſuteable Encouragements by the 32d. <hi>Act, Par.</hi> 1693. and by the 8th. <hi>Act, Par.</hi> 1695. Yet both theſe Laws
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50338:11"/>were granted with a due regard to all former Planters;
<q rend="margQuotes">And did only allow them to plant Colonies, build Cities, Towns, and Forts in <hi>Aſia, Africa,</hi> and <hi>America,</hi> upon Places not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited, or in, or upon any other Place, by Conſent of the Natives, or Inhabitants there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and not poſſeſſed by any <hi>European</hi> Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign, Potentate, Prince or State.</q>
               </p>
               <p>By theſe Acts of Parliament, and Patent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, His Majeſty did ſufficiently provide, that the Poſſeſſion of no <hi>European</hi> Prince ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded or moleſted: And if <hi>Spain</hi> be injured, the Company muſt acknowledge, that the Injury flows from them, by exceeding the Limits of their Patent.</p>
               <p>It remains to be cleared in behalf of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, that they have ſtrictly obſerved the Rules preſcrib'd by the ſaid Acts and Patent.</p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s Title to <hi>America</hi> by the Pope's Bull, is rejected by the common Conſent of all the Princes and States in <hi>Europe,</hi> who could not have ſettled there without Injury to <hi>Spain,</hi> if the Pope's Bull had been a ſufficient Title; and neither <hi>Spain</hi> or <hi>Portugal</hi> hath relyed upon that Title, the one having planted in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> and the other in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> without regard to it: And this Title is ſufficiently diſcuſſed by <hi>Grotius</hi> in his <hi>Mare Liberum, Cap.</hi> 3. and will never be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted on any where, and leaſt of all in <hi>Brittain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>America</hi> being inhabited by Natives, before <hi>Spain</hi> or any <hi>European</hi> People ſettled there, it is moſt certain, that the Right and Property did o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginally belong to theſe Natives, becauſe the Earth was created for, and freely given by the Creator to the Children of Men, and the moſt Ancient and Uncontraverted Right of Property
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50338:11"/>of the Earth is by Occupation and Poſſeſſion, which is an outward Act of the Body <hi>quaſi poſitio pedis,</hi> and not an inward Act of the Mind, which cannot be known to others, beſide many Mens wills might concur in wiſhing and liking the ſame thing, but their Bodies cannot concur in poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it, and an outward Act of Poſſeſſion warns others to abſtain.</p>
               <p>The Property that originally belonged to the Natives, could only be transferred from them to <hi>Spain</hi> by Conqueſt or Conſent, and <hi>Spain</hi> can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend neither of theſe Titles to the <hi>Iſthmus</hi> where the <hi>Scots</hi> have ſettled.</p>
               <p>It is alledg'd for <hi>Spain,</hi> That they do poſſeſs the <hi>Iſthmus</hi> of <hi>Darien,</hi> in as far as they are undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Maſters of the Bay of <hi>Panama,</hi> and the whole Coaſt of the <hi>Iſthmus</hi> upon the South Sea: They have likewiſe <hi>Carthagena</hi> and <hi>Portobella</hi> on the North Sea, and they are Maſters of the whole Countrey betwixt <hi>Carthagena</hi> and <hi>Portobello,</hi> and ſo muſt be reckoned Poſſeſſors of all, becauſe Poſſeſſion doth not require the particular Occupation of every part of a Countrey, but Occupation of one part is a ſufficient Act to demonſtrate the Will and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to poſſeſs the whole Pertinents: And the <hi>Spaniards</hi> having poſſeſs'd theſe two Extremes, the middle Space belongs to them, eſpecially ſeing they have alſo ſettled in other Places betwixt theſe two, as their Conveniency did require, tho' they did afterwards quite theſe Poſſeſſions, as particularly they once poſſeſſed <hi>Nombre de Diot,</hi> and did alſo plant within the River <hi>Datien,</hi> and tho' they did quite theſe Poſſeſſions, they did not relinquiſh or repudiate their Right, but being better informed, they chooſed more convenient Seats, but ſtill reckoned themſelves Proprietors of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50338:12"/>the whole <hi>Iſthmus,</hi> and divided the ſame in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Juriſdictions. And the Natives upon that <hi>Iſthmus</hi> were a mean inconſiderable People not to be regarded, who could not be thought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any Right or Property in Oppoſition to the Power of <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They further add, That <hi>Spain</hi> hath been conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as undoubted Proprietors of the Bay of <hi>Mexico,</hi> and of that <hi>Iſthmus,</hi> by other Nations in Chriſtendom, and moſt particularly by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as is well known, and will clearly appear in two remarkable Inſtances.</p>
               <p>Several <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants having advanc'd their Stock, for ſettling a Plantation at <hi>Port-Royal</hi> in the Bottom of the Bay of <hi>Campechay,</hi> for cutting of Logwood, they deſired the Countenance and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of the Government, for carrying on this profitable Trade: The Caſe was conſidered by the Council of <hi>England,</hi> and it was not found juſt, to allow the Protection of the Government, but were only left in a Permiſſive State, to manage their Trade upon their Peril.</p>
               <p>The Second Caſe, which comes cloſer to the preſent Queſtion, was a Propoſal by certain <hi>Engliſh</hi> Undertakers to ſettle in <hi>Darien,</hi> as the <hi>Scots</hi> have done, which being brought to the Council of Trade of <hi>England,</hi> and by them laid before the Lords Juſtices in His Majeſties Abſence, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the King himſelf, Upon a full Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the Caſe, that Project was thought to be an Encroachment upon <hi>Spain,</hi> and let fall.</p>
               <p>The King himſelf, and Council of <hi>England,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſatisfied of the Right of <hi>Spain,</hi> in theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Caſes of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Undertakers, the ſame judgment ought to follow, in relation to the Sco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Company.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:50338:12"/>
               <p>To all that is alledged, it's ſhortly and clearly Anſwered, That <hi>Spain</hi> hath neither Right by Treaties nor Poſſeſſion to the Countrey now poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd by the <hi>Scots:</hi> And, 1ſt. Tho' it be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd, that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> have more Strength, and larger Poſſeſſions on the South, than upon the North Sea, yet no Poſſeſſion there can be exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the North-ſide of the <hi>Iſthmus,</hi> being poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd by a People Independent, who never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> or became ſubject to them: The <hi>Spaniards</hi> indeed have made great Settlements upon the South Sea, and in ſo far as they have poſſeſs'd, have reſtricted the Natives to narrower Bounds; but the <hi>Indians</hi> ſtill continuing to poſſeſs what remains, Poſſeſſion on the Coaſt, or the Mouths of Rivers on the South Sea, can never be extended to the North Coaſt: And the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard</hi> can condeſcend upon no Ground in Law or Reaſon for ſuch an Extenſion, hor can they make appear, that what the <hi>Scots</hi> poſſeſs is Part and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiennt of their Plantation, eſpecially conſidering that the <hi>Iſthmus</hi> of <hi>Darien</hi> is naturally divided by a Ridge of high Hills running from Eaſt to Weſt.</p>
               <p>Neither doth the poſſeſſion of <hi>Carthagena</hi> and <hi>Porto-bello,</hi> give Right to the interveening Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, which is above 80 Leagues or 240 <hi>Engliſh</hi> Miles, and theſe particular Forts, as well as the whole <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Plantations on the South Sea, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fixt without conſent of the Natives, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue their Poſſeſſion in the interveening Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, without any Subjection to, or acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Spaniard:</hi> It lyes upon the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to condeſcend by what Rule the Limits of theſe Poſſeſſions can be ſo far extended.</p>
               <p>As to what is alledged, That the <hi>Spaniards</hi> have other Plantations nearer to the <hi>Scots</hi> Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50338:13"/>from which they removed, but ſtill retain Poſſeſſion and Juriſdiction.</p>
               <p>It is Anſwered, Admitting the matter of Fact as alledged, it comes to nothing; For ſtill it is to be remembred, That the <hi>Spaniard</hi> will not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to have planted with the conſent of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives: Nor, that the <hi>Darien Indians</hi> have ever ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg'd Subjection; but they planted by Force and Violence: And therefore, whatever Forts they made in the <hi>Isthmus</hi> of <hi>Darien,</hi> the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that theſe Plantations were left, the Right and Poſſeſſion of the Natives did return.</p>
               <p>It is freely acknowledged, That Poſſeſſion lawfully obtain'd by an outward Act of the Body, is retain'd by Acts of the Mind, if no other poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs; but when Poſſeſsion is taken by way of Fact, and not actually detained, the Right and Poſſeſsion returns to the lawful Proprietor.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This alledged Poſſeſsion of <hi>Nombre de Dios,</hi> and in the <hi>River of Darien,</hi> is only pretended to have been at their firſt Settlement in <hi>America,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they poſſeſs'd <hi>Carthagena</hi> and <hi>Porto-bello.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. None of theſe pretended Settlements are within 20 Leagues of the <hi>Scots</hi> Colony; And tho <hi>Spain</hi> had yet Plantations there, the Limits could as little be extended to 20 Leagues beyond the actual Poſſeſsion as to a Thouſand: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can the <hi>Spaniards</hi> prove any Act of Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over the <hi>Darien Indians,</hi> whatever Title they may think fit to give to Governours or Vice-Roy's in <hi>America,</hi> the <hi>Scots</hi> do neither know, nor are oblig'd to notice the ſame: If Titles were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, the King of <hi>Spain</hi> aſſumes a Glorious Title of <hi>Indiarum Rex,</hi> but he has no more Juriſdiction over the <hi>Darien Indians,</hi> than in the Plantations of any other <hi>European</hi> Prince.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:50338:13"/>
               <p>As to what is alledg'd upon the Opinions given by the King and Council of <hi>England,</hi> in relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to His Majeſty's <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects projecting Settlements in <hi>America,</hi> The Circumſtances of the Projects, and the Motives of any Reſolution taken in them, are wholly unknown to the <hi>Scots,</hi> and nothing can be founded on ſuch Matters of Fact, unleſs the whole Circumſtances were Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentically inſtructed or acknowledg'd, but what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever was thought proper in theſe Caſes, nothing can be inferred from thence to determine this.</p>
               <p>A Project is to be regulated either by Law or by Conveniency; And it's very ordinary and ſute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, That his Majeſty and the Government may diſcourage the Project of an Undertaking, if not Convenient, tho lawful: But when a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject is Undertaken, Carried on, and a Settlement made in purſuance of expreſs Acts of Parliament, and conform to a Patent, there's no more place to Deliberate what is fit, but what is Lawful.</p>
               <p>If the whole Circumſtances were known, many Diſparities might alſo appear, and from the bare relation of the Caſe of the intended Settlement in the Bay of <hi>Campeohay</hi> a manifeſt Diſparity is evident.</p>
               <p>The Bay of <hi>Campechay</hi> is in the Province of <hi>Nicaragua,</hi> in the Dioceſs of <hi>Chiapo,</hi> which Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince and Biſhoprick, are part of the Ancient <hi>Empire</hi> of <hi>Mexico,</hi> which was conquered by <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the Conqueſt of <hi>Mexico,</hi> the King of <hi>Spain</hi> as Conquerour, had Right of Sovereignty as far as the Dominions of <hi>Mexico</hi> did extend, and the Right and Poſſeſsion of the Conquered People may reaſonably be reckoned to become the Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsion of the Conquerour; And therefore a Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>Nicaragua</hi> or Bay of <hi>Campechay</hi> might be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50338:14"/>reckoned a down Right Encroachment upon <hi>Spain,</hi> which cannot be drawn in Conſequence to a Settlement upon <hi>Darien,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Spaniards</hi> can condeſcend upon no Title or Right beyond their actual Poſſeſsion; for the <hi>Dariens</hi> were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſubdued, nor did they ever depend upon <hi>Mexico</hi> or <hi>Peru,</hi> or any Prince or People ſubdued by the <hi>Spanirds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And further, whatever be urged from theſe Caſes, yet it can be made appear, That the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking to ſettle in <hi>Campechay</hi> was effectual, and the Cart is marked <hi>Port-Royal Engliſh-Colony;</hi> and 'tis known that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> cutt Logwood at <hi>Cape-Catach</hi> in <hi>Jucatan</hi> till the Charge of Carriage ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd it unprofitable, and thereafter Settled at <hi>Port-Royal</hi> for the ſame Effect, where there is plenty of Logwood appropriated to the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is alſo acknowledg'd, That the <hi>Darien-Indians</hi> are no powerful People, or able by themſelves to reſiſt the Impreſsions of <hi>Spain,</hi> but the point of Right and Property is the ſame in Rich and Poor, Strong and Weak, and they might lawfully transfer their Right, and aſſume the <hi>Scots</hi> or any other Nation to ſupport or maintain the Right and Poſſeſsion of that <hi>Isthmus,</hi> in as far as it was free from the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Dominions.</p>
               <p>Yet the <hi>Dariens</hi> were not wholly neglected by the <hi>Spaniards</hi> as inconſiderable, for there have been frequent and almoſt conſtant Wars between them and <hi>Spain,</hi> in which the ſeveral Captains and <hi>Carriques</hi> have joyned together, and there is a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Caſe of <hi>Barth: Sharp,</hi> who being accuſed in <hi>England</hi> as guilty of Piracy and Robbery commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon the <hi>Indians,</hi> he defended himſelf as acting by Commiſsion from Independent Native <hi>Indians</hi> then at War with <hi>Spain,</hi> and was acquitted.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:50338:14"/>
               <p>The Right of the <hi>Scots</hi> Colony, as flowing from the Native <hi>Indians,</hi> is already ſufficiently cleared, according to the moſt Ancient and Authentick Laws of Property, acknowledg'd by all Nations: And for a further Evidence and Demonſtration of what has been aſſerted, and already ſufficient-proven the Settlement of the <hi>Engliſh, French, Danes, Portugueſes,</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> will all be found to be Bottomed on the ſame Ground.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> are the moſt Ancient Planters, and if <hi>Spain</hi> pretend to any Univerſal Title, either by Occupation of a part, or by the Popes Gift, or any other Right, he thereby excludes the Claim of all Poſterior Planters, either in the Continent, or <hi>American</hi> Iſlands, which could not be thought to be ſeparate and indifferent Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions: And if <hi>Spain</hi> recede from any Univerſal Title to the whole, it will not be poſsible to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend his Claim beyond his proper Poſſeſsion, or the Poſſeſsions of theſe that are Subduced and Conquered by <hi>Spain:</hi> And if this be called in Queſtion, it is expected, That ſome other Title will be condeſcended upon, that may clear the Limits and Extent of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Colonies, ſo as to make a Difference betwixt the <hi>Scots</hi> Settlement in <hi>Darien,</hi> and the Settlement of other Princes in the <hi>American</hi> Iſlands or Continent.</p>
               <p>The Empires of <hi>Mexico</hi> and <hi>Peru</hi> are known, and may be yielded to <hi>Spain,</hi> but the remainder of that vaſt Countrey was anciently poſſeſs'd by little Princes, or rather Captains or Heads of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies or Cariques, who have no Dependance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on each other, nor upon any Prince or Potentate, but by Leagues and Agreement for mutual De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. Thus it is known, That the Land of the <hi>Amazons</hi> was poſſeſs'd by the Natives; And it is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50338:15"/>remarkable, That upon the Banks of <hi>Amazon,</hi> there are Fifty different Nations: So it is in <hi>Braſil,</hi> in <hi>Chili, Paragua, Florida, Carolina, Virginia,</hi> and generally over all the Continent, as well as in the Iſlands of <hi>America,</hi> and likewiſe in <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Africa:</hi> And therefore, <hi>European</hi> Princes have planted promiſcuouſly, as they found Convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, without Injury or Encroachment upon for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Planters.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> poſſeſs the Continent from <hi>New-England</hi> to <hi>Carolina,</hi> without the Interpoſition of Colonies belonging to any <hi>European</hi> Prince, yet the <hi>Dutch,</hi> in time of Peace, ſet down upon <hi>Long-Iſland,</hi> and the Countrey now called <hi>New-York,</hi> betwixt <hi>New-England</hi> and <hi>Penſilvania,</hi> and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued to poſſeſs till the end of the War 1667: At which time, <hi>New-York</hi> was exchanged for <hi>Suranam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Plate-Fleet do neceſſarly paſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Cape-Florida</hi> and the <hi>Bahaman-Iſlands,</hi> yet the <hi>Engliſh</hi> poſſeſs theſe Iſlands, which the <hi>Spaniards</hi> did mightily reſent, and uſed the <hi>Engliſh</hi> very bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſly upon it, yet <hi>Spain</hi> not being able to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy any unlawful Title, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> did maintain their Poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p>Whatever be alledg'd, That the Government did not interpoſe for eſtabliſhing a Logwood-Trade, yet it's certain, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate the Logwood at <hi>Cape-Catch</hi> in <hi>Jucatan,</hi> till it was exhauſted, and they afterwards ſettled at <hi>Port-Royal</hi> in the Bay of <hi>Campechay,</hi> for carrying on the ſame Trade, which was never queſtion'd by the <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>French</hi> have ſeveral times endeavoured to ſettle in the River <hi>de Spiritu Sancto</hi> in the Bay of <hi>Mexico,</hi> and alſo the <hi>Samballo-Iſlands</hi> upon the Coaſt of <hi>Darien,</hi> and have actually ſettled a Colony in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50338:15"/>
                  <hi>Petit-Guavis</hi> in <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> the reſt of that Iſland being poſſeſt by the <hi>Spaniards:</hi> The <hi>French</hi> have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a Settlement in <hi>Guiana</hi> in the <hi>Terra-Firma,</hi> and ſeveral Forts upon the Coaſt of <hi>Caribana,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove twelve or thirteen <hi>American</hi> Iſlands.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Dutch</hi> have alſo the City of <hi>Coro</hi> in the North of <hi>Terra-Firma,</hi> and <hi>Suranam,</hi> and certain Forts upon the Coaſt of <hi>Guiana</hi> and <hi>Curaſao,</hi> and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>American</hi> Iſlands.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Portugueſe</hi> have the Coaſt of <hi>Braſil</hi> divided into many Captainſhips. The Intereſt of <hi>Spain</hi> was ever oppoſit to all theſe Settlements in <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica,</hi> and wherever they were ſtrong enough, they attempted to expel the Planters, without regard to Peace or War, whereof the <hi>Scots</hi> did formerly feel the Effects, in their Plantation at <hi>Carolina</hi> hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> from whence they were expelled: Theſe things were done by way of Fact, but it is the firſt time that ever <hi>Spain</hi> did openly pretend a Right beyond actual Poſſeſſion, which was never ſuſtained by any <hi>European</hi> Prince. And it is deſired and expected, that there may be a further Condeſcendance of the Right and Title of <hi>Spain,</hi> to exclude other Planters by the Conſent of the Natives, where <hi>Spain</hi> hath no actual Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, or Exerciſe of any Juriſdiction.</p>
               <p>It is further alledged for <hi>Spain,</hi> That all the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs in <hi>America</hi> was ſettled by the Pacification 1670, betwixt the Kings of <hi>Brittain</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> which did confirm all the Plantations poſſeſs'd by <hi>Engliſh</hi> Colonies, and left the Remainder of <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica</hi> to <hi>Spain,</hi> and whatever happened before that General Treaty, could be no Rule thereafter, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there was almoſt perpetual War with <hi>Spain</hi> in <hi>America,</hi> which were never ſettled or compoſed till the Treaty 1670, which did preſuppoſe and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50338:16"/>the Right of <hi>Spain</hi> to all that was not poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the King of <hi>Brittain</hi>'s Subjects.</p>
               <p>As to the Inſtance of <hi>Sharp,</hi> it is not denyed that he was acquitted, and amongſt others did propone that Defence, That he Acted by Commiſſion from an <hi>Indian</hi> Prince; but that Defence was look'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as a Jeſt, and it was not for that Reaſon that he was acquitted.</p>
               <p>It is Anſwered, There was indeed a Treaty in the Year 1670, concerning <hi>America</hi> in particular, whereby it was provided, <q rend="margQuotes">That the King of <hi>Brittain</hi> ſhould have, hold and enjoy for ever, with full Right of Sovereignty, Dominion and Property, all thoſe Lands, Regions, Iſlands, Colonies, and Places whatſoever ſituated in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> or any part of <hi>America,</hi> which the ſaid King and his Subjects did then hold and poſſeſs;</q> From which Article the <hi>Spaniards</hi> would infer, that all the reſt of <hi>America</hi> was loſt by the King of <hi>Brittain,</hi> as a Right and Dominion of <hi>Spain,</hi> becauſe that <hi>Spain</hi> ratifies the Poſſeſſion ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the King of <hi>Brittain,</hi> and there is not a mutual Ratification of the Poſſeſſion of the King of <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Article can bear no ſuch Inference, for,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The King of <hi>Brittain</hi> and his Subjects did not then, nor do they now in the leaſt queſtion the Poſſeſſions of the King of <hi>Spain</hi> and his Subjects, but the King of <hi>Spain</hi> did very much queſtion the Right of the King of <hi>Brittain</hi> to ſeveral of his <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rican</hi> Plantations, not only upon the general Ground of an Univerſal Title to all the <hi>Weſt-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> which no <hi>European</hi> Prince will bear, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe upon particular Claims, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had beat out the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and enjoyed what had been once poſſeſs'd by them in ſeveral places: And the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50338:16"/>former Treaties with <hi>Spain</hi> eſpecialy that in the Year 1667, were only general, eſtabliſhing a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Peace betwixt the Dominions and Terito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of <hi>Brittain</hi> and theſe of <hi>Spain:</hi> But the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion remaining anent the Right and Dominion of theſe <hi>American</hi> Settlements to which the King of <hi>Spain</hi> did lay ſtill a Claim, The Treaty 1670, did renounce his Claim to the Colonies in the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Poſſeſsion, but did determine nothing as to thoſe parts of <hi>America,</hi> which were never Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd by the <hi>Spaniard</hi> or <hi>Brittiſh,</hi> and if it had been intended, that the Right of <hi>Spain</hi> to all <hi>America</hi> that was not poſſeſs'd by ſome other <hi>European</hi> Prince ſhould be aſſerted, and declared the ſame would not have been left to ſuch remote conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, but would have been ſpecially expreſs'd.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The whole Tenor of that Treaty does ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently clear, that no ſuch thing was intended as to preſuppoſe, much leſs to aſſert the Right of <hi>Spain</hi> beyond actual poſſeſſion. For by the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Article of the Treaty, it is provided, <q rend="margQuotes">That there be an Univerſal Peace in <hi>America,</hi> as in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of the World between the Kings of Great <hi>Brittain</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> and between the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, States, Plantations, Colonies, Forts, Cities, Iſlands and Dominions belonging to either of them; and between the People and Inhabitants under their reſpective Obedience.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This Article in the Treaty relating to <hi>America,</hi> only doth clearly demonſtrate, that both Kings were ſet upon an equal foot, and did Treat for themſelves and the People and Inhabitants under their reſpective Obedience, and no further; ſo that all matters were left untouched that did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern parts not Inhabited or poſſeſs'd by Natives, who were never under obedience to either Prince,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50338:17"/>nor would the Treaty have been for Plantations, Colonies, Forts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> equally and mutually, if either King had pretended an univerſal Title or Right beyond Poſſeſsion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Eight Article doth yet further clear, that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> had no Univerſal Claim, but according to his Poſſeſsion, which Article provides, that the Subjects, Inhabitants and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners of the Dominions of each Confederate, ſhall forbear to Sail to, or Trade in the Ports and Havens which are fortified with Caſtles, Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zines or Ware-Houſes, and in all other. Places whatſoever, poſſeſs'd by the other Party in the Weſt <hi>Indies.</hi> To wit, the Subjects of Brittain ſhall not Sail into, and Trade in the Havens and Places, which the Catholick King holds in the <hi>Indies,</hi> nor in like manner ſhall the Subjects of the King of <hi>Spain</hi> Sail into, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Clauſe is, plainly reſtrictive upon the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> That the Subjects of the King of <hi>Brittain</hi> ſhall not Trade into theſe places of the <hi>Indies</hi> which belong to <hi>Spain;</hi> for thereby it preſuppoſes that <hi>Spain</hi> has no Univerſal Title, and its left free to the King of <hi>Brittains</hi> Subjects to Sail into, and Trade in all Ports and Havens which have no Fortifications, Caſtles, Magazines, or Ware-Houſes Poſſeſs'd by the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently it was lawful to have Sailed to, and Traded with the <hi>Darien Indians</hi> where the King of <hi>Spain</hi> had no Fortifications, Caſtles, Magazines or Ware-Houſes, nor can clear any manner of Poſſeſsion, and if they might Trade with the <hi>Indians</hi> it muſt be acknowledg'd they might Settle among them.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">It's alſo provided by the Tenth Article, that in caſe the Ships of either Party be forced
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:50338:17"/>by ſtreſs of Weather, or otherwiſe into the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, Creeks, Bays or Ports belonging to the other in <hi>America,</hi> they ſhall be treated there with all Humanity and Kindneſs;</q> Which Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle ſtates both Kings again upon an equal foot, and mentions the Right of both as reſtrictive to particular Rivers, Creeks, Bays, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in <hi>America</hi> as if neither Party claimed Univerſal Title over all.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">The 15th. Article of the ſaid Treaty pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides, that the ſame ſhall in nothing derogate from any preheminency, Right or Dominion of any Confederate in the <hi>American</hi> Seas, Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels or Waters, but that they have and retain the ſame in as full and ample manner as may of right belong unto them, providing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways that the Liberty of Navigation ought in no manner to be diſturbed.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This Article relates to certain Preheminencies and Priviledges claim'd by <hi>Spain</hi> in the <hi>American</hi> Sea, which by the Treaty was not yeilded, but left in the ſame ſtate as formerly; and if the King of <hi>Spain</hi> had pretended to an Univerſal Right o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all <hi>America,</hi> in ſo far as is not poſſeſs'd by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>European</hi> Princes, why was he more carefull to preſerve his Claim of Sovereignty in the Seas, and forgot his Dominion upon the main Land? There can be no other reaſon for it, but becauſe there was no ſuch thing in proſpect, as appears by the whole Tenor of the Treaty.</p>
               <p>Nothing hath been alledged in behalf of <hi>Spain</hi> to make any diſparity betwixt all the Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that have been made in <hi>America</hi> by the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the King of <hi>Brittain</hi> or other Princes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Treaty 1670: Which when duly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, makes no diſparity at all. For albeit the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:50338:18"/>Poſſeſsion of the King of <hi>Brittains</hi> Subjects be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by confirmed; yet it will not be acknowledg'd by the King of Great <hi>Brittain,</hi> or any other Prince that the Settlements made by their Subjects were illegal or violent, untill confirmed by the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and all Nations who have Planted there muſt ſuſtain and juſtify the <hi>Scots</hi> Settlement, or acknowledge that the Settlement of their own Subjects were injurious to the Right of <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not, nor can be denyed, that the <hi>Dariens</hi> have been at frequent War with <hi>Spain,</hi> altho' they pretend, that the <hi>Dariens</hi> were rather Rebels than Enemies. That is only for to beg the Queſtion, for the Natives having the Ancient undoubted Right, it muſt be inſtructed, that they became Subjects before they could be Rebels.</p>
               <p>And tho' it be alledged, that what was done in <hi>Sharp</hi>'s Caſe was reckoned a Jeſt, and that he was not acquitted upon that ground, as acting by Commiſsion from the <hi>Dariens;</hi> yet the matter of Fact is certain and known, and was indeed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marked by all <hi>England,</hi> that <hi>Sharp</hi> join'd with the <hi>Dariens,</hi> did commit acts of Hoſtility and carried away great booty from the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and was purſued for Reſtitution in <hi>England,</hi> and did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pone a Defence. That he acted by Commiſsion from an Independent People, and was acquitted by a competent Judicature in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe matters of Fact being all acknowledged, it muſt be thought that a Deciſion in the way of Juſtice was no Jeſt, but according to the Law of the Nation.</p>
               <p>To Conclude and Sum up the whole Matter, The <hi>Scots</hi> did not move one foot, untill they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd two Acts of Parliament, and a Patent in their favours. Theſe Acts (tho' very ample)
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:50338:18"/>were framed with a juſt regard to former Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, who by the expreſs Tenor of the ſaid Laws were not to be invaded or moleſted in their Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion; even the juſt Right and Property of the Infidel Natives was conſidered, and the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers not allowed to diſpoſſeſs them by Force and Violence, but to Plant with their conſent: Upon the faith of theſe Laws, a greater Stock was advanced in <hi>Scotland</hi> than ever was raiſed by any other Nation, upon the firſt project of a Forreign Plantation; the Directors of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany did very narrowly and exactly conſider all the Treaties with <hi>Spain,</hi> and pitched upon a place, that the whole World conſiders to be of a great value for founding and raiſing a profitable Trade to the Honour of the King who (as the Father of the Countrey) did endue them with ample and juſt Priviledges, to the encreaſe of the Strength and Riches of the Iſle of <hi>Brittain,</hi> which is all under the Government of one Monarch, of one Religion and Intereſt, and can have no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Friends or Enemies without endangering the whole. In one word, The <hi>Scots</hi> Company have acted deliberatly, for advantage to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the Nation, and the Iſle of <hi>Brittain;</hi> they have only uſed their own Right and have wronged no Nation or People, nor exceeded the Limits of their Patent in any circumſtance. And if any will ſtand up for the Intereſt of <hi>Spain,</hi> and call in queſtion the matters of Fact and principles of Law above aſſerted, which are generally known and need not to be confirmed by particular Citations. they may aſſuredly expect that what has been affirmed ſhall be made further clear and evident beyond contradiction, and whatever Obſtacles
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:50338:19"/>or Difficulties have, or may fall in, <hi>Ardua quae Pulchra,</hi> the undertaking was deliberate, juſt for the intereſt of the Nation, and with more regard to the Right of former Planters and Natives than any former Project of that Nature.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="further_reading">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>WHoever would be furniſhed with any more Arguments for proving the legality of the Settlement of <hi>Caledonia,</hi> and with a full account of all the conſiderable occurrences relating there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto may have his judgment ſufficiently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, and his Curioſity abundantly gratified by reading the following Books.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>A Defence of the</hi> Scots <hi>Settlement at</hi> Darien.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>A ſhort and impartial view of the manner and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of the</hi> Scots <hi>Colony's coming away from</hi> Darien.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>An Enquiry into the Reaſons of the Miſcariages of the</hi> Scots <hi>Colony at</hi> Darien, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>A juſt and modeſt Vindication of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he</hi> Scots <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign for the having eſtabliſhed a Colony at</hi> Darien.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>A full and exact Collection of all the conſiderable Addreſſes, Memorials, Petitions, Anſwers, Proclamations, Declarations, Letters and other Publick Papers relating to the Company of</hi> Scotland <hi>Trading to</hi> Africa <hi>and the</hi> Indies, <hi>ſince the paſſing of the Act of Parliament, by which the ſaid Company is eſtabliſhed, together with the Act it ſelf,</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:50338:19"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
